<?xml version="1.0" encoding='ISO-8859-1'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- $Id$ -->

<chapter id="user.geostat">  
 <title><indexterm><primary>Geostatistics</primary></indexterm>
 Geostatistics</title>
 <subtitle>Plugin geostat</subtitle>
                                    
 <sect1 id="user.geostat.inter">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <para>
   This chapter describes how to configure geostatistics functionnalities.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="user.geostat.concepts">
  <title>General behaviour</title>
  <para>
   The Geostat plugin allows advanced cartographic representation based on 
   attributes of geospatial data. Currently, there is only support for 
   polygonal entities. There will be support for ponctual symbol very soon. 
   Every vectorial formats supported by Mapserver may be use.
  </para>
  <para>
   The client side of the plugin allow the specification of the mandatory and 
   optional paramaters. These parameters will be passed to the server side 
   which will create the map layer and return some informations about the 
   dataset.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="user.geostat.server">
  <title>Server-side Configuration</title>
  <sect2 id="user.geostat.server.mapserver">
   <title>Mapfile Configuration</title>
   <para>
    On the server side, the first configuration step is made within the mapfile.
    The only requirement is a least on polygonal layer which expose at least one
    attribute. You may consider an attribute as exposed if you can use it as 
    CLASSITEM for this layer. You must add one (and only one) class to this 
    layer. It will be use as template for the generated classes. You may use
    this class to define border color, label or other default parameter.
    You should not add this layer to the <filename>layers.ini</filename> 
    configuration file.
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="user.geostat.server.ini">
   <title><filename>geostat.ini</filename> Configuration</title>
   <para>
    Choropleth layers are managed differently then ordinary layer within 
    cartoweb. <filename>server_conf/mapId/geostat.ini</filename> is used to 
    define layers that may be used for geostatistics. Take a look to a sample
    of this file.
   </para>
     <programlisting>
    <![CDATA[
geostat.0.mslayer = region_geostat_fill
geostat.0.label = Region
geostat.0.choropleth = true
geostat.0.choropleth_attribs = POPULATION,HOUSINCOME
geostat.0.choropleth_attribs_label = "Population","Average house income"]]>
  </programlisting>
  <para>
   These example represents a single layer definition. The general for of 
   parameter is geostat.<parameter>n</parameter>.<parameter>key</parameter> = 
   <parameter>value</parameter>. <parameter>n</parameter> is an incremental 
   number (first layer of the config file is 0. <parameter>key</parameter> is 
   a parameter for this layer. <parameter>value</parameter> is the value 
   associated to the following parameter. The following parameters defined 
   choropleth generation :
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para><parameter>msLayer</parameter> : name of the layer in the mapfile
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para><parameter>label</parameter> : Label for the layer in the interface
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para><parameter>choropleth</parameter> : Should choropleth be activated. 
    This is present for future development</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para><parameter>choropleth_attribs</parameter> : Comma separated list of
    attributes that may be used for choropleth</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para><parameter>choropleth_attribs_label</parameter> : Comma separated 
    list of labels to display as description of the preceding attributes</para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="user.geostat.client">
  <title>Client-side Configuration</title>
  <para>
   Client-side configuration allow to specify which algorithms should be display
   within the user interface. Currently, there are 2 algoriths families that
   may be configured. The first is about classification algorithms. The
   second is about generation of color ramp. The signification of the parameter
   is pretty straightforward. 
  </para>
  <programlisting>
    <![CDATA[
;The following classification method are currently supported
;   Custom : 0
;   Equal intervals : 1
;   Quantils : 2
;   Modes : 3
choroplethClassifMethodDefault = 2
choroplethClassifMethodsList = 0,2,3
;The following color ramp generation method are currently supported
;   Custom : 0
;   RGB interpolation : 1
;   HSV interpolation : 2
;   Max diffrence : 3
choroplethColorRampMethodDefault = 1
choroplethColorRampMethodList = 1,3]]>
  </programlisting>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
