<?xml version="1.0" encoding='ISO-8859-1'?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % cartoweb SYSTEM "../cartoweb.ent" >
  %cartoweb;
  ]>
<chapter id="user.linkIt">
  <title>Saving Map Context as an URL <subscript>[plugin] (exportLinkIt)</subscript></title>
    <para>The exportLinkIt plugin displays in &cartoweb; interface a URL that saves the main caracteristics of the current page.
    Saved data are selected layers, layers switch id, recentering info (center and scale), mapsize as well as outlined shapes 
    and map queries.
    </para>
  <sect1 id="user.linkIt.activate">
    <title>Plugin Activation</title>
      <para>
        To activate the plugin, add it to 
        <parameter>loadPlugins</parameter> from &cartoclient; configuration file: 
        <filename>client_conf/client.ini</filename>.
        For instance: <programlisting>loadPlugins = exportLinkIt</programlisting>
      </para>
      <para>
        You also need to add the plugin output variable <parameter>{$linkIt}</parameter> into the project main template <filename>templates/cartoclient.tpl</filename> (see upstream template for instance). It is recommended to add it outside of the main &cartoweb; &lt;form&gt; tag since the generated HTML may contain an additional &lt;form&gt; tag. Use CSS to place the result box.
      </para>
      <para>
        Ajax is used to generate and display the resulting URL, using the Prototype Javascript Framework. If your &cartoweb; does not run in the <parameter>ajaxOn</parameter> mode, you need to add the Prototype file in the main template <filename>templates/cartoclient.tpl</filename>. To do so add the following HTML code within the &lt;head&gt; tag: <programlisting><![CDATA[{if $linkIt|default:'' && !$ajaxOn}<script type="text/javascript" src="{r type=js}prototype.js{/r}"></script>{/if}]]></programlisting>
      </para>
      <para>Also add the CSS file inclusion in <filename>templates/cartoclient.tpl</filename>:
      <programlisting><![CDATA[{if $linkIt|default:''}<link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="{r type=css plugin=exportLinkIt}linkIt.css{/r}" />{/if}]]></programlisting>
      </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="user.linkIt.config">
    <title>Plugin Configuration</title>
      <para>Generated URL GET parameters may be obfuscated or "compressed" by setting the <parameter>compressUrl</parameter> to <parameter>true</parameter> (default is <parameter>false</parameter>) in <filename>client_conf/exportLinkIt.ini</filename>. When obfuscation/compression is activated, regular URLs (with standard &cartoweb; GET parameters) are still accepted.</para>
      <para>Generated URL may be rather long and thus overflow browsers or servers limits. <parameter>urlMaxLength</parameter> can be used to  make &cartoweb; output a warning message when the generated URL is longer than the specified value.</para>
      <para>For instance:</para>
      <programlisting>compressUrl = true
urlMaxLength = 2000</programlisting>
      <note><para>
        The Generated URL will only contains the query parameters if the queried layers have the <emphasis>id_attribute_string</emphasis> metadata specified in the mapfile! (see <xref linkend="user.query.mapfile.metadata"/>)
      </para></note>
  </sect1>

</chapter>

