<?xml version="1.0" encoding='ISO-8859-1'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3.0//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3.0/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="user.location">
 <title>Spatial options</title>
 <subtitle>Plugin location</subtitle>
 <partintro>
  <para>
  The plugin location is the core plugin that deals with geographic navigation
  on the map. It handles bboxes (visible areas) and scales; it drives the tools
  zoom-in, zoom-out and panning, the directional arrows around the main map and
  the overview map.
  </para>
  <para>
  The corresponding configuration files are <filename>location.ini</filename> (client-side) 
  and <filename>location.ini</filename> (server-side).
  </para>
 </partintro>
 <sect1 id="user.location.client"> 
  <title>location.ini (client-side)</title>
  <para>
  Here are the options that can be set :
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
    <indexterm>scalesActive</indexterm>: boolean, if true, the scales dropdown list is displayed (default: false). 
    If no visible scales are defined on the server, a simple input text will be displayed.
    </para>
   </listitem>
      <listitem>
    <para>
     <indexterm>recenterActive</indexterm>: boolean, if true, the coords recentering form is displayed (default: false)
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <indexterm>idRecenterActive</indexterm>: boolean, if true, the id recentering fields will be displayed (default: false)
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <indexterm>shortcutsActive</indexterm>: boolean, if true, the shortcuts (direct access dropdown list) are displayed (default: false)
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <indexterm>scaleUnitLimit</indexterm>: scale above which DHTML measures use km ; below, they use m.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <indexterm>panRatio</indexterm>ratio for panning by clicking directional arrows. 
     Default is 1 (no overlap, no gap). Values below 1 result in an overlap of the old and the new maps; 
     values above 1 in a gap between these two maps.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <indexterm>weightZoomIn:</indexterm>: integer defining display order of the zoom_in tool icon in toolbar 
     (if not specified, default to 10). A negative weight disables the tool.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <indexterm>weightZoomOut:</indexterm>: see weightZoomIn (default to 11)
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <indexterm>weightPan:</indexterm>: see weightZoomIn (default to 12)
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>

</chapter>

