<?xml version="1.0" encoding='ISO-8859-1'?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
 "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % cartoweb SYSTEM "../cartoweb.ent">
  %cartoweb;
]>
<!-- $Id$ -->
<chapter id="user.wmslight">
 <title><indexterm><primary>wmslight</primary></indexterm>WMS Browser Light</title>
  <sect1 id="user.wmslight.intro">
   <title>Introduction</title>
   <para>
   <parameter>wmsBrowserLight</parameter> plugin allows you to add WMS layers to your map using the ogcLayerLoader plugin. 
	Main difference between the wmsBrowerLight and the wmsBroser plugin is the managment of the server list. The plugins manage
	WMS servers compatible with version 1.1.1 of the OGC WMS spec..
	
	Using the wmsBrowerLight plugin you have three ways to add specify the server end point (url). 
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Simply type in the text box the server you heard about like http://mywmsserverurl.iheard.about (Do not set the version 
		or any other parameters). 
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>  
		<para>Define a list of WMS servers using the ini file of the plugin. The servers will be presented to the end user in 
		a list box.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>  
		<para>Connect to a GeoNetwork node having metadata on WMS services and load server urls from this catalog. </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="user.wmslight.activation">
    <title>Plugin Activation</title>
    <para>
        To activate the plugin, load ogcLayerLoader from both CartoClient and CartoServer configuration files
	 and wmsBrowserLight plugins from CartoClient configuration files: 
        <filename>client_conf/client.ini</filename> and 
        <filename>server_conf/"mapId"/"mapId".ini</filename>. For instance:
        <screen><![CDATA[
loadPlugins = mapOverlay, ogcLayerLoader, wmsBrowserLight
        ]]></screen>
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="user.wmslight.ini">
    <title>Define a list of WMS servers using the ini file</title>
    <para>
	To do so, in <filename>client_conf/wmsBrowserLight.ini</filename>, set the following parameters in the ini file of the plugin.
    
	<screen>
		catalogtype = ini
		
		servers.0.label = Sandre / Ouvrage
		servers.0.url = http://services.sandre.eaufrance.fr/geo/ouvrage

		servers.1.label = Données administratives et routières en France (Geosignal)
		servers.1.url = http://www.geosignal.org/cgi-bin/wmsmap
	</screen></para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="user.wmslight.gn">
    <title>Connect to a GeoNetwork node having metadata on WMS services</title>
    <para>In order to use this type of connection the name of the GeoNetwork node has to be known. 
		Optionnaly, the plugin will first logged into the node if user and password are specified. 	
	To do so, in <filename>client_conf/wmsBrowserLight.ini</filename>, set the following parameters in the ini file of the plugin.
    
	<screen>
		catalogtype = gn
		gn = http://sandre.eaufrance.fr/geonetwork
		; unset gnuser and gnpassword if no login has to be made
		gnuser = cartoweb
		gnpassword = cartoweb
		gnlang = en
		; gnQuery is how CartoWeb could get the list of services in the node
		gnQuery = "category=Services"
	</screen></para>
	<para>
		For the time being, there is no way to query GeoNetwork for services in a consistent manner using the ISO 19115 information. 
		It should be possible to get this information from the tag ScopeCd of the DataQuality section. But this is not 
		a searchable criteria in version 2.0.2. On tip is to create on the GeoNetwork node a category set to "services" 
		and then used this categrory to get the list of server to propose to the end user.
	</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
